<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Poem upon His Majeyst's [sic] happy return from Ireland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55269</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15020457</idno>
  <idno type="VID">103055</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240924434</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35113</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15020457</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1576:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Poem upon His Majeyst's [sic] happy return from Ireland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:103055:1"/>
            <head>A POEM UPON <hi>His Majeyst's Happy Return</hi> FROM IRELAND.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WElcome Victorious Prince, once more</l>
               <l>From Conquer'd <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the British Shoar.</l>
               <l>How soon has thy Illustrious Name</l>
               <l>Eclips'd the vaunting <hi>Caesar</hi>'s Fame?</l>
               <l>For thou art only He</l>
               <l>That went, and view'd, and overcame.</l>
               <l>Fresh Laurels here attend</l>
               <l>The Nations Sov'raign, and the Nation's Friend,</l>
               <l>Rewafted once again,</l>
               <l>Endanger'd <hi>England</hi> from her fears to free.</l>
               <l>The wary <hi>Schombergh</hi> fought by Rule and Art,</l>
               <l>And cautiously spun out the time;</l>
               <l>But when Heroick <hi>WILLIAM</hi> came to act his Part,</l>
               <l>Success seem'd only lodg'd in Him;</l>
               <l>And all Pretence of Right,</l>
               <l>From the belov'd of Heav'n took speedy flight.</l>
               <l>One would have thought,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Richard</hi> would have <hi>Henry</hi> fought:</l>
               <l>He that so oft had given out</l>
               <l>What he would do in person, more than <hi>Castor</hi> stout.</l>
               <l>But his amazing Guilt</l>
               <l>Before decided, did the Issue dread;</l>
               <l>And to preserve Anointed Head,</l>
               <l>In Consternation from the Danger fled.</l>
               <l>Danger, That Princely <hi>WILLIAM</hi> seem'd to Court,</l>
               <l>And She by chance approach'd;</l>
               <l>But having once in View</l>
               <l>Th' undaunted Awe that sat upon his Brow,</l>
               <l>Danger it self with-drew, and only touch'd</l>
               <l>The Daring Venturer, Heav'ns kind pow'r to show.</l>
               <l>Then say no more,</l>
               <l>That Fortune rules the World, or that Her Pow'r</l>
               <l>To Royal Thrones extends:</l>
               <l>She has no share</l>
               <l>In the Success of doubtful War;</l>
               <l>Nor is it on Her frowns</l>
               <l>That the Repose of Rule depends.</l>
               <l>Long, though her Champions in her weak Defence,</l>
               <l>'Gainst Heav'n have brandish'd Human Eloquence;</l>
               <l>They need not Imp their <hi>Icarus</hi> wings</l>
               <l>From soaring Flight to fall</l>
               <l>Upon the Rocks of Learned Ignorance.</l>
               <l>Trace but Heav'nsConduct, they shall find,</l>
               <l>It was not Chance,</l>
               <l>Or any Change that Fortune sends,</l>
               <l>That hasten'd <hi>James</hi>'s sudden fall,</l>
               <l>Or Potent <hi>WILLIAM</hi> did advance,</l>
               <l>To Soveraign State, and Dignity of Kings.</l>
               <l>Let 'em to fresh Remembrance call,</l>
               <l>How oft with Shields of Angels covered o'er,</l>
               <l>In dismal Fight he stood</l>
               <l>'Midd'st Peals of Thunder, and in show'rs of Blood.</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103055:2"/>
               <l>How but of late</l>
               <l>The hasty Bullets lost their Sulphur'd Heat,</l>
               <l>And tamely tumbl'd at his Horses Feet.</l>
               <l>How disappointed Treachery combind</l>
               <l>By Pious Plots, and Holy Undermines</l>
               <l>Of those that take, ne'er swallow Oaths,</l>
               <l>To ruin all his Great Designs,</l>
               <l>And blast the Labours of his pondering Mind:</l>
               <l>But disappointed still, to show</l>
               <l>They moyle in vain, that muse his Overthrow.</l>
               <l>Hard Case howe'er, to be betray'd at home</l>
               <l>By the black Tools of <hi>FRANCE</hi> and <hi>ROME,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While he was forc'd abroad, the Stygian Boggs to cleanse,</l>
               <l>And free the Passage to assist his Friends:</l>
               <l>As if 'twere still the noblest <hi>Hero</hi>'s Fate,</l>
               <l>That they must visit Hell</l>
               <l>Before they can be Great.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All these Reflections might convince</l>
               <l>Th' unthinking <hi>Jacobites</hi> unruly Sense,</l>
               <l>That still the great unfinish'd Work goes on;</l>
               <l>Not to Perfection to be brought,</l>
               <l>But by the Princely <hi>WILLIAM</hi>'s Hand alone,</l>
               <l>Th' Imperial Eagle his long wisht for Leisure waits,</l>
               <l>And all the late afflicted States,</l>
               <l>And wronged Princes send to him for Aid,</l>
               <l>To wreck their just Revenge</l>
               <l>On him that on their fair Dominions prey'd.</l>
               <l>All this the Gallick <hi>Diomed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That has so long his Horses fed</l>
               <l>With Human Blood, and Orphans Bread,</l>
               <l>With Terror does behold,</l>
               <l>And throws about his ill-got Gold</l>
               <l>To tempt unwary Fools.</l>
               <l>Affrighted <hi>Lewis</hi> dreads the Storm</l>
               <l>To see the Mettl'd English Arm,</l>
               <l>And maugre all his feigned Ironies,</l>
               <l>Quits distant Conquests and unites his Force.</l>
               <l>Thus the Alarum'd Blood doth change it's Course,</l>
               <l>And to the Heart, when once distemper'd, flies.</l>
               <l>And now, what can we less portend</l>
               <l>But that those Lawrels, fresh and green,</l>
               <l>Planted by our victorious Monarchs Hand,</l>
               <l>In his Auspicious Reign will grow</l>
               <l>To Cedar Heighth, and bear</l>
               <l>New Trophies every Year?</l>
               <l>His Lawrels are not common; yet if such</l>
               <l>Scorn the Celestial Thunders touch,</l>
               <l>When prepared for his Brow;</l>
               <l>We must not then allow,</l>
               <l>That <hi>France</hi>'s Thunder more than Heav'ns can do.</l>
               <l>May then each Year of his long Reign,</l>
               <l>Still be Crown'd,</l>
               <l>With Successes far and near;</l>
               <l>And every day be still renown'd</l>
               <l>With some splendid Act of Glory,</l>
               <l>To enlarge our Monarchs Story;</l>
               <l>For Years, the chiefest in Renown,</l>
               <l>Live by the Princes Fame, and not their own.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>